Chapter 3: Too Quiet

Author's Notes: I'm on TV Tropes! Everything I've ever wanted.

Today's Character Sheet: myth-weavers com/sheetview php?sheetid=553596

"So, anything interesting happen over the summer?" Hermione asked curiously. "I mostly just read—I read Gadding with Ghouls, Break with a Banshee, and Travels with Trolls four times and Year with the Yeti five, but I only had enough time to read Voyages with Vampires twice! Hopefully I can get in another round of each before September."

Vampires, eh? Milo thought to himself, wondering whatever happened to Quirrell's—no, Voldemort's—vampires from the year before. As far as he knew, they were still out in the Forbidden Forest, lurking.

The four of them—Harry, Ron, Hermione, and Milo—were waiting outside Madam Malkin's while Ginny got her school uniform. It was the first time they'd seen Hermione since June.

"Nope," Milo said quickly.

"What, nothing?" Hermione asked.

"Nothing at all," Ron added, avoiding eye contact. "We were well-behaved."

"Well, that's a relief—since you've done your readings, maybe this year you can do your own homework." Hermione paused. "You have done the readings, haven't you?"

"Look over there!" Ron gasped. "It's the Grim!" In truth, they didn't even have their textbooks yet. Acquiring them was one of the objectives of their current sidequest.

"Sorry, where?" Hermione turned around, surprised, to where Ron was pointing. However, instead of a pernicious prognostication, there was merely Ollivander's—or Ollivanders'?—wand shop, which, in Milo's mind, was only marginally better.

"Must have been my imagination," Ron said quickly. "Shall we, er, go see Quality Quidditch Supplies? Oh, but you two don't like broomsticks. Have fun doing—er—thing!" Grabbing the surprised Harry Potter by his shirtsleeve, Ron practically bolted away through the crowded alley, dragging the bemused Boy-Who-Lived behind him.

"What was that all about?" Hermione asked suspiciously.

"No idea," Milo lied, cursing his friends for abandoning him. He'd have to rely on his Bluff skill. Come on, nat twenty, don't fail me now... "Because he certainly wasn't fleeing to avoid telling you about a disaster—which, and I can't stress this enough—certainly didn't happen in late July."

Hermione stared at him for a second or two, her expression unreadable. "I see." She totally bought it! You've still got it, Milo. "Because I thought he was making a runner because he hadn't actually done any advance reading and didn't want to fess up about it."

"Oh, yes, that's much more believable. Let's go with that. Which reminds me: I should probably go get this year's reading list. And I need to send a letter. Want to come with?"

"Well, seeing as how the others have fled my presence, I don't see any particular reason why not. What letter?" Hermione asked curiously.

"My Amulets of Protection from Evil—now that I can make them cheaply, I'm planning to offer them to Ministry."

"That's a really good idea," Hermione approved. "From what I've read, one of the largest problems they had there in the last war was being unable to determine who was under the effects of the Imperius curse, or, even if they could, to counter it. They're still trying to sort out who may have been compromised."

"Exactly. That, and the fact that I can charge whatever I want for them." If the Ministry was interested, he could finally pay Harry back for the small fortune he borrowed from him last year. Material costs aside, he still had to pay the XP cost, meaning he couldn't just give them away—even if he had the time to.

"We can go to the Owl Post Office, and by the time we're done, likely Harry and Ron will have forgotten why they ran off in the first place," Hermione suggested.

The Owl Post Office, as it turned out, was exactly what it sounds like. Owls—Milo still couldn't understand why these wizards relied on owls for post, especially when there were not one but two forms of teleportation (Apparating and Floo powder) available—fluttered in and out through the largely open roof to the floor, where frantic postal workers tied fresh parchment to their legs and beleaguered janitors used magic and enchanted mops in a futile attempt to keep the room clean. And that wasn't even getting to the noise. The screech of owls and massed flutter of wings was nearly deafening.

"Morgana's ghost!" Hermione gasped. "It smells like a dung bomb went off in here!"

Milo, choking, wrapped a black silk filter mask from his belt around his face, covering it from the eyes down. While he doubted the smell was poor enough to force him to make a Fortitude save, he wasn't taking any chances.

"How do the employees tolerate it?" Milo asked. Unfortunately, his newfound appreciation for taste had the side-effect of drastically increasing his perception of non-plot-relevant scents. In addition to being a minor hindrance to his plot sense, it could also be extremely annoying.

"Bubble-Head Charm?" she suggested. "Although you'd think that long-term reliance on a small volume of recycled air would weaken the immune system..."

"I think they get enough contact with unsanitary material through other means to make up for that," Milo pointed out. After... certain events last year, he'd decided to spend some time over the summer researching basic medical theory in this world—enough that there wouldn't, hopefully, be a repeat of last Christmas but not enough that he was forced to invest skill ranks cross-class in Heal. "I'd be more worried about what happens to wizards and witches with bad breath."

An obviously-stressed young wizard was sitting behind the counter. His fingernails had all been chewed to the quick, his hair was in disarray, his lips were cracked and his eyes were a bloodshot red—the latter two likely a result of his face being continuously surrounded in dry air for eight hours every day. The source of his problems was evident, as there were scratch-and-peck-marks up and down both arms, layered over scars of earlier ones.

"Are we being robbed? Oh Merlin, we're being robbed!" the post-wizard exclaimed, taking note of Milo's masked face before bolting into a back room, followed by a muffled "Colloportus!"

"Er..." Hermione said. "Is there someone else we can talk to?" she asked the room. Eventually, a post-witch showed up, gave them a lecture about scaring their elders, took Milo's letter (and silver) and shooed them out.

"Well, that was decidedly odd," Hermione murmured as they left.

"Agreed," Milo said. "Let us never speak of this place again."

They found Harry and Ron leaving whatever the broomstick shop was called—Milo honestly couldn't care less—and they headed to the bookstore. Milo noticed that Ron and Harry conspicuously kept him between them and Hermione.

The bookstore, as it turned out, was largely empty. Books lined the tall, narrow shelves (in Milo's experience, you could always tell the quality of a bookstore by how cramped the aisles were. By that metric, this one was pure mithril), although most of the textbooks, the store's major draw in August, were already gone. A few posters hung from the walls, each depicting the same handsome man's smiling face.

"Who's he?" Milo asked.

"Gilderoy Lockhart," Ron shrugged. "He's supposed to be this big, famous dark wizard hunter, but his book on dealing with household pests is pretty rubbish."

"That's probably because he's too busy fighting werewolves and vampires to brush up on his dealings with doxies and pixies," Hermione said defensively, browsing through a stack of Miranda Goshawk's The Standard Book of Spells, Grade Two . "Which would be obvious if any of you had actually read your textbooks."

"Hold up," Ron said. "How did you get a hold of them so early? This is the first time you've been to Diagon Alley all summer, right? Or you'd have your other supplies, too."

"You have heard about owl order, haven't you?" she said, although she turned slightly pink.

"Then how come you didn't get the Book of Spells, too?" Harry asked innocently.

Hermione muttered something about a "standing pre-order," shot them an acid look, and went to the counter.

"So, this Gorilla Lockout guy," Milo said thoughtfully. "He's a dark wizard-hunter-type?"

"Pretty much," Ron said. "But if you ask me, he's just famous because the witches, and not a few wizards, all fancy him."

"And he wrote our entire booklist?" Milo pressed.

"Looks like—except for the one by Goshawk," Harry said, scanning over his letter from Hogwarts.

"And he was mentioned earlier this adventure?"

"Er..." Harry said, giving Milo the usual look.

"Dammit," Milo muttered. "Another DADA professor. Now, the question remains—will he prove to be secretly treacherous, like Quirrell, or will he break the expectation created by the precedence of the last professor to be, in fact, secretly good despite our suspicions?"

"Your suspicions, mate," Harry said.

"The poster says he was going to be here yesterday doing a book signing," Ron said. "We would have met him if we hadn't been... delayed."

"The important thing is we were let off with a warning," Harry said, "and we can put that entire ordeal behind us. Permanently."

"What ordeal?" Hermione asked, returning with her newly-purchased textbook.

"Ordeal? What ordeal?" Ron asked.

"He meant to say ore deal," Milo lied. "We're discussing the acquisition of certain metals of arcane significance for my... magicking." Milo sighed inwardly—you get what you pay for, and he hadn't invested any ranks in Bluff.

"Right," Hermione said skeptically. "Are you three just going to stand around talking, or will you actually get the books you came here for?"

Milo and Ron coughed and discreetly stepped towards the 'used' section. Milo had been sent a sum of money from Hogwarts' Destitute Orphans' Fund this summer that was so modest it was practically bashful. Even used, there was no way he would be able to cover the extensive Lockhart booklist without dipping into the money Harry had lent him for spell research and item crafting.

"What say you we go half-half," Milo suggested quietly to Ron, "then put the Pen of Plagiarism +5 to work?"

"Won't work," Ron said, "all Flourish and Blotts' books are protected against Copying Cha..." Ron drifted off as the penny dropped. Milo's magic would, likely, be able to bypass that protection—although the results could sometimes be unpredictable when the two types of magic interacted.

Ron simply grinned.

"Well, well, well," an unfortunately familiar voice drawled. "If it isn't three jailbirds and their pet mole—oh wait, is that Granger behind those horrid teeth?"

"Malfoy," Harry said through clenched teeth. Draco Malfoy stood leaning against a shelf near the entrance. None of them had seen him enter.

"I'm surprised you'd dare show your faces in public," the blond Slytherin boy continued. "I hear Weasley's father had to use his last remaining favour in the Ministry to get you three off the hook—and himself, for that matter. What was it he said? That that car was simply for experimenting, and not for using? Rather slim excuse, if you ask me, but it pales in comparison to what you did. Tell me, where there many rats in the Muggle prison? Aside from you and your... pets."

"Frankly, I thought you'd learned your lesson last time," Harry said, "as I believe Milo here knocked your teeth in."

"Check your facts, Potter," Malfoy sneered. "I only lost one tooth! And don't think you won't pay for that—and what you did to my house."

"A mistake I'm all too ready to remedy," Milo said, putting down Gadding with Ghouls in case he needed his hands for a fight. "And that time, you had the Crabbegoyles with you. Now, the numbers are somewhat stacked against you."

"I wouldn't sully these pureblood fists with your face, freak, even if I was here to fight," Malfoy said contemptuously. "I was simply so surprised to see your faces in public after your little ordeal that curiosity simply required me to determine that it was you, and not some illusion or charm—though I needn't have worried. Charm is not something any of you has in abundance."

"Ooh, a Slytherin with a sharp wit," Ron said with feigned awe. "Someone take it away before he cuts himself with it."

Malfoy gave Ron a look as if he were something sticky he scraped off the bottom of his shoe, and turned to leave. Not being one to allow anyone else to have the last word, he spun around dramatically before leaving the store. "I'll be seeing you at Hogwarts, I presume—though when you discover what's going to happen this year, perhaps you'll wish you'd stayed home with your mothers. Except you, Harry."

Draco slammed the door shut behind him.

"Anyone want to bet that he doesn't yet have a plan and he's, right this second, frantically trying to come up with one to match his boast?" Harry said after a second.

"I feel like I'll regret this, but... you're on," Ron said. "Wonder how he found out about—" Ron froze, and turned to stare at Hermione in horror.

"You were arrested? By the police? The Muggle police?" Hermione gasped.

"Milo thought I was in danger," Harry explained.

"He had bloody convincing reasoning, too," Ron added. "A very solid argument. I'm not sure what it was, mind; you'll have to ask him yourself."

"And what reason... never mind. Obviously the dastardly threat to Harry was Milo's impending rescue," Hermione said.

"I think there's something funny with your logic there," Milo said, as he tried to imagine whether it was possible that he could have dropped out of a timeskip due to himself being the threat, in which case he had only dropped out of the timeskip because of what he was about to do after dropping out of the timeskip, which would make for some kind of self-fulfilling, loopy causality. Even thinking about it was beginning to give him a headache, and so he let it rest.

"Now my logic is funny?" Hermione remarked wryly.

"To be fair," interjected Harry, grinning, "Being jailed by the Muggles was a lot more fun than being jailed by the Dursleys. I'd say it was a pretty top-notch rescue."

o—o—o—o

What remained of the summer holidays flew past at the rate of just a few scant words of description per week, with Harry and the Weasleys (which sounded to Milo like a pretty good name for a Bardic troupe) spending most of their time playing Quidditch—a game which, while he approved of it from the dramatic standpoint of making only the PCs and their actions matter, Milo disdained because it involved physical exertion and the ability to ride broomsticks—while Milo tried to keep a low profile. His recent glimpses of the Muggle world had shaken him to a degree that surprised him. They seemed to be able to accomplish the impossible without magic—like cars, for instance. Milo could think of a few means of moving a wheeled vehicle without animal power: the wheels or the whole vehicle could be animated, it could be sail-powered with a permanent Gust of Wind, it could be a tiny, mobile stronghold, or, most cost-effectively, it could be moved by controllable poltergeist spirits via Animate Dead and Hauntshift. However, all of Milo's plans were either prohibitively expensive in terms of gold, XP, or morals—and, of course, required magic. The more Milo thought about it, magic was really the limiting factor. Magic, save for some trickery relying on extreme Munchkinry, came hand-in-hand with exponential—and fixed—time, gold, and XP costs. Mundane crafting had none of these concerns, with the time being largely based on the creator's skill, tools, and assistants and the cost fluctuating with circumstance and quality. From what he'd seen, the Muggles here nearly all had cars. It boggled the mind. An ordinary peasant from Myra (City of Light! City of Magic!) would have to spend nearly three years' wages to buy a good horse and wagon, and all of Milo's proposed self-propelled machines would cost hundreds of times more—except possibly for the last, depending on the availability of relatively intact, low-HD corpses.

He'd owled Hermione, who had gone back to live with her parents until September, to ask how the Muggles managed to make so much stuff. She'd asked her mother, and sent back what amounted to a short essay detailing mining, machinery, smelting, and, the production line. Milo had scoffed at the idea of 1st level non-caster NPCs working together to create goods en masse—until he did the math. Ninety-nine unskilled Commoners, and one with 4 ranks and Skill Focus in the proper Craft skill, with one set of Masterwork Tools, all using Aid Another (which would give each a 50% chance to add +2) would have a colossal +108 Craft bonus. Using Quick Crafting, higher bonuses would lead to exponential returns. This group could make around thirteen thousand silver pieces worth of goods in a week—compared to the seven silver piece weekly wage they could expect working alone. With other bonuses, such as those from feats, better tools, or a decent Intelligence bonus, that number would increase dramatically. Sure, a Wizard could simply cast Fabricate and turn any raw material into any finished product, but Fabricate required a 9th-level Wizard, and how many thousands of level one Commoners were there per 9th-level Wizard?

That led Milo down another track. A horrifying track. It came to him when he tried to explain the differences between the Muggles here and those in Myra (City of Light! City of Magic!). He didn't know anything about the state of Muggles outside of England—or, to be honest, outside of Little Whinging—so generalizations were risky. But, even assuming that England was the wealthiest, most powerful empire on this plane, when compared to the Azel Empire, of which Myra (City of Light! City of Magic!) was capital, there were horrifying conclusions. Azel was one of the wealthiest human empires from his world. Nevertheless, its average citizens—the NPC commoners—lived in a near-perpetual state of poverty and fear. They had to rely on the happenstance of a passing party of adventurers for protection, and could hardly afford food, much less shelter, as a simple one-room wooden cottage went for 1,000gp (10,000 days' wage) anywhere in the realm. Most people lived in lean-tos built out of quarterstaffs and clubs, thatched with holly and mistletoe, and the other few free items in the book. Their only options for escape were to become another random encounter—that is, banditry—or adventuring. Both options offered the chance at a fortune, but came at the cost of having a terrible retirement plan (the business end of a passing Paladin's longsword or a Red Dragon's stomach, respectively). But the Muggles here, in England, had food, safety, and homes. They had a competent city watch. It was then that Milo realized the reason for it: magic. The wizards here kept their magic a secret for reasons that seemed entirely selfish: the Muggles would never stop bothering them, because they would want magical solutions to all of their problems. In Milo's world, magic was no secret. It was available, it was open. There was a magical solution to any problem—for a price. There was no need to develop a superior plow when you could hire a Druid to cast Plant Growth. The reason was clear, and it would keep Milo awake at night: magic throttled innovation. In History of Magic, Milo had learned that this world had passed through an era that roughly resembled his world. But the medieval era, as it was called, came and went in a few hundred years. A few hundred years was a blink. It was window-dressing. It was a rounding error. Adventurers routinely investigated ruins of civilizations hundreds of thousands of years old that had access to comparable—or even, if their traps were any indication, superior—mundane technology. Hells, Malbutorius the Dark, an epic-level Lich with a soul blacker than the sun isn't, had been a thorn in the side of humanoid civilization since the dawn of time. Even the Elves couldn't remember a time when he didn't exist. Milo's world was locked in stasis, and the only reasonable explanation for it was magic.

"Are you coming, or what?" Ron asked him, waving a hand in front of his face.

"Sorry," Milo apologised. "I was..." he was going to say 'in an internal monologue,' but he doubted they had those here. "thinking how we could get back at Malfoy." They were standing in front of Platform Nine and Three-Quarters, and the others had all gone through already. Well, nothing for it... Milo ran at the wall, not even having the scant comfort of having luggage ahead of him, in case the barrier unexpectedly turned solid—Milo kept all of his possessions, save for his mountain of salt, in his Belt of Many Pouches.

Despite his concern, he came through the solid-looking wall without problem, followed shortly by Ron.

"Do any of you have a... funny feeling?" Milo asked the group.

"Not another one," Hermione groaned.

"What do you mean?" Harry asked.

"Well, it's like... remember what I told you last year?"

"Er..."

"About how everything we'd see in the early days of the adventure would be important for later," Milo clarified.

"Right, that," Harry said. "What about it?"

"It might be too early to say, but... well, things just haven't been ominous enough," Milo said. "Before you say anything, I know it's a ridiculous thing to complain about. But, frankly, as it is, I have no idea what to expect this year. Have any of you heard any, I don't know, whispered conversations that broke off abruptly when you came near? Or had any foreboding dreams?"

"Nope," Ron admitted.

"Sorry," Harry said. "None of those."

"Maybe it'll be a normal year," Hermione said wistfully, "and we'll be able to focus on our studies and futures."

"Yeah... maybe..." Milo couldn't help but feel as if he was missing something critical as he boarded the train.

On the far side of the platform, Ginny pulled out her new quill (really a hand-me-down from Charlie) and dipped it into her new inkpot (really a hand-me-down from Bill) to hurriedly write in her new leather-bound diary (really fifty years old, but it was, unlike all of her other possessions, so far unused). September 7th, 1992, she began. Dear diary, I am about to step on the famous Hogwarts Express (!) for the first time, and I'm very excited-and-sort-of-nervous, though Harry Potter hasn't even noticed me, yet...

o—o—o—o—o—o—o

D&D Tip: The filter mask is an extremely under-appreciated piece of gear. Available for a measly 1gp from Sandstorm (p.99-100), it grants a +2 against gas-based effects (think traps, Stinking Cloud, maybe even Cloudkill) as well as significant situational bonuses against sandstorms. Also a necessary fashion choice for anyone who wants to play FFI's Red Mage or a ninja of one variety or another. From a purely mechanical standpoint, there's no reason why anyone wouldn't wear one. Besides, who doesn't like keeping track of more conditional modifiers?

D&D Tip #2: The crafting trick really works. If wages become tricky to handle, use undead. The problem is that there's a maximum number of skeleton HD you can control that way, based on your level. Make a magic item of Animate Dead 1/day, and pay random commoners to use it for you, and order the resulting abominations to follow your orders. The skeletons don't have to be humans, in fact, I believe it's funniest if they're squirrels. Undead have the advantage of not requiring sleep, so they can work 24 hours per day instead of the usual 8, tripling their effectiveness. With Int -, they have a +0 crafting bonus, so roughly half of them can successfully aid another. They can aid you, or, if you're out adventuring, just aid a regular skeleton. The silver piece value they can make in a week is around, depending on what you craft, 3*((10+skill bonus)^2).

If you have trouble justifying to your DM that nonintelligent squirrel skeletons could make masterwork swords (or whatever), describe it as less of a workshop and more of a production line. Each skeleton does something minor, like move a certain tool or object in a specific way ad infinitum. Each squirrel does one step (a single hammer blow, a single scrape with a whetstone) and passes it to the next squirrel.

That's just the tip of the iceberg. If raw material cost (1/3rd of the finished product) becomes a problem, use Walls of Iron. 50gp raw materials and 660gp of casting fees produces a lot more than 710gp of iron, which is 1sp/lb. A CL 11 Wall of Iron produces 11*5*5*(1/6)=45.833 cubic feet of iron, which is 22,527lbs, which is 11,263.5gp in raw materials. But double-check that, math is not my strong suit.

Or you could skip the skeletons and just sell raw iron. As a commodity, its value isn't halved for sale. Cha-ching!

(Don't actually do this)